Guide to the Child Study Center, School of Medicine, Yale University, Records Concerning the Longitudinal Study
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Child Study Center, School of Medicine, Yale University, records concerning the longitudinal study
1942-2002
RU 282
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
61.37
(129 boxes)
The records consist of notes, reports, photographs, and interviews documenting the longitudinal study conducted at the Child Study Center, Yale School of Medicine.
Yale University. Child Study Center
Conditions Governing Access
Series I, II (boxes 53-55), III, IV (boxes 59-84), and V are restricted until 2050. Researchers wishing to use the records before this date must secure written authorization from the Arnold Gesell Professor of Child Psychiatry, Pediatrics, and Psychology, Yale Child Study Center.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies (designated by a box with a 'U' suffix), or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
The Yale longitudinal study was planned as an ambitious exploratory study of personality (ego) development in the first years of life. The research team was composed of pediatricians, child psychologists, nursery-school teachers, psychiatric social workers and psychoanalysts, specialists in early childhood development. The initial investigators, including Ernst Kris, Sally Provence, then-director Milton Senn, Charlotte del Solar and Katherine Wolf, began to recruit families and pilot the data collecting apparatus in early 1950.
Potential subjects were approached after their first obstetrical contact at the Yale-New Haven Hospital. Mothers were recruited if they were white, married, between eigthteen and thirty-five years, expecting their first child, presenting no severe physical or mental health complaints, expecting to reside in the vicinity of New Haven for several years, and if they expressed interest in participation.
Twenty-two families were initially recruited. Eventually ten families were followed completely, and there are also records for another six discontinued subjects. The collection of data for the study proper began in 1950. In its original conception the children were to be followed from birth through their first five years of life, but as the study progressed some subjects continued to be followed well into their teenage years.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of notes, reports, photographs, and interviews documenting the longitudinal study conducted at the Child Study Center, Yale School of Medicine.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in five series: I. Family Data, 1950-1990s. II. Administrative Files, 1950-1982. III. Photographs, no date. IV. Katherine Wolf Records, 1942-1963. V. Data on Families (duplicates), 1950-1964.
General
Formerly manuscript collection MS 1967.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of William Kessen, 1989 and 1999. Transferred from the Child Study Center, Yale University, 1996, 2000-2001, 2014. Gift of Deborah Trofatter, 2011.
General
Forms part of Yale Record Group 27-E (YRG 27-E), Records of departments, offices, programs, and projects of the Yale School of Medicine.
Child psychiatry -- Research -- Longitudinal studies; Child psychology -- Research -- Longitudinal studies; Developmental psychology -- Longitudinal studies; Psychiatry -- Research -- Longitudinal studies; Yale University. Child Study Center; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Family data, 1950-1990s; Series I
  Conditions Governing Access
  This material is restricted until January 1, 2050. Researchers wishing to use the records before this date must secure written authorization from the Arnold Gesell Professor of Child Psychiatry, Pediatrics, and Psychology, Yale Child Study Center.
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of the data collected on individuals and families, including observations, interviews and reports. The data is arranged by "research" name assigned to the families. Only "research" names are included in the listing.
  - Dunn
    - Volume I, 1950 December-1952 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Volume II, 1952 May-1953 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Volume III, 1953 May-1954 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Volume IV, 1954 May-1955 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Volume V, 1955 November-1956 December (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Categories, 1950-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Summary record, 1953 March-1957 June (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Follow-up
      - 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Writings, 1959, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Korwich
    - Volume I, 1951 June-1952 November (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Volume II, 1952 December-1953 November (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Volume III, 1953 December-1954 June (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Category record, 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Meredith
    - Volume I, 1950 December-1952 June (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Volume II, 1952 June-1953 May (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Volume III, 1953 June-1954 October (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Volume IV, 1954 November-1955 April (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Volume V, 1955 May-October (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Volume VI, 1955 November-1956 April (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Volume VII, 1956 May-December (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Volume VIII, 1957 January-September (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Volume IX, 1957 October-1958 May (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Categories, 1952-1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Follow-up, 1955-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - Writings, 1953-1983 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Monahan
    - Volume I, 1950 December-1952 June (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Volume II, 1952 June-1953 April (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Volume III, 1953 June-1954 April (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Category record, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Nitos
    - Volume I, 1951 July-1952 September (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Volume II, 1952 October-1953 October (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Volume III, 1953 October-1954 August (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Volume IV, 1954 September-1958 December (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Category record, 1951-1958 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Summary record, 1953-1959 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Follow-up and writings, 1956-1958, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Olsen
    - Beth
      General
      Volume numbers 1-6 were used twice; volumes can be differentiated by date spans.
      - Volume I, 1951 March-1952 April (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Volume II, 1952 May-1953 April (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Volume III, 1953 October-1955 May (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Volume IV, 1955 June-December (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Volume V, 1956 January-September (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Volume VI, 1956 October-1958 April (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Volume I, 1957 September-1958 July (Box 13, Folder 3)
        This folder is marked "family study".
      - Volume II, part 1, 1958 September-December (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Volume II, part 2, 1958 December-1959 March (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Volume II, part 3, 1959 March-July (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Volume III, part 1, 1959 September-1960 January (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Volume III, part 2, 1960 January-March (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Volume III, part 3, 1960 March-July (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Volume IV, part 1, 1960 September-December (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Volume IV, part 2, 1961 January-April (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Volume IV, part 3, 1961 April-July (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Volume V, part 1, 1961 September-December (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Volume V, part 2, 1962 January-April (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Volume V, part 3, 1962 April-July (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Volume VI, 1962 December-1963 May (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Volume VII, 1963 December (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - George
      - Volume I, 1955 October-1958 July (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Volume II, part 1, 1958 September-December (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Volume II, part 2, 1958 December-1959 March (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Volume II, part 3, 1959 March-July (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Volume III, part 1, 1959 September-1960 January (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Volume III, part 2, 1960 January-March (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Volume III, part 3, 1960 March-July (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Volume IV, part 1, 1960 September-December (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Volume IV, part 2, 1961 January-April (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Volume IV, part 3, 1961 April-July (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Volume V, part 1, 1961 September-December (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Volume V, part 2, 1962 January-April (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Volume V, part 3, 1962 April-July (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Volume VI, part 1, 1962 September-1963 June (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Rennie
      - Volume I, 1957 September-1958 July (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Volume II, part 1, 1958 September-December (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Volume II, part 2, 1958 December-1959 March (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Volume II, part 3, 1959 March-November (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Volume III, part 1, 1959 September-1960 January (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Volume III, part 2, 1960 January-March (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Volume III, part 3, 1960 March-July (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Volume IV, part 1, 1960 September-December (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Volume IV, part 2, 1961 January-April (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Volume IV, part 3, 1961 April-July (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Volume V, part 1, 1961 September-December (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Volume V, part 2, 1962 January-April (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Volume V, part 3, 1962 April-June (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Volume VI, part 1, 1962 September-1963 July (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Volume VII, 1963 September-1964 January (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Sally
      - Nursery school
        - Volume I, 1958 January-June (Box 23, Folder 4)
        - Volume II, 1958 September-1959 May (Box 23, Folder 5)
        - Volume III, part 1, 1959 September-December (Box 23, Folder 6)
        - Volume III, part 2, 1960 January-March (Box 24, Folder 1)
        - Volume III, part 3, 1960 March-May (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Therapy
        - Volume II, part 3, 1959 January-July (Box 24, Folder 3)
        - Volume III, part 1, 1959 September-1960 January (Box 24, Folder 4)
        - Volume III, part 2, 1960 January-March (Box 24, Folder 5)
        - Volume III, part 3, 1960 March-June (Box 24, Folder 6)
        - Volume IV, part 1, 1960 September-December (Box 25, Folder 1)
        - Volume IV, part 2, 1961 January-April (Box 25, Folder 2)
        - Volume IV, part 3, 1961 April-July (Box 25, Folder 3)
        - Volume V, part 1, 1961 September-December (Box 26, Folder 1)
        - Volume V, part 2, 1962 January-April (Box 26, Folder 2)
        - Volume V, part 3, 1962 April-July (Box 26, Folder 3)
        - Volume VI, part 1, 1962 September-December (Box 27, Folder 1)
        - Volume VI, part 2, 1963 January-March (Box 27, Folder 2)
        - Volume VI, part 3, 1963 April-July (Box 28, Folder 1)
        - Volume VII, 1963 November-1964 June (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Family
      - Biographical and clinical introduction, 1954, 1955, 1959 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Calendars
        - Volume I, 1957-1958 (Box 32, Folder 1)
        - Volume II, 1958-1959 (Box 32, Folder 2)
        - Volume III, 1959-1960 (Box 32, Folder 3)
        - Volume IV, 1960-1961 (Box 32, Folder 4)
        - Volume V, 1961-1962 (Box 32, Folder 5)
        - Volume VI, 1962-1963 (Box 32, Folder 6)
      - Categories, 1951-1958 (Box 33, Folder 1-3)
      - Family interactions
        - 1958 January-April (Box 33, Folder 4)
        - 1951 March-1952 September, 1958 September-December (Box 33, Folder 5)
        - 1960 September-October (Box 34, Folder 1)
        - 1960 September-1961 May (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Formulations
        - Miscellaneous, 1959-1961 (Box 34, Folder 8)
      - Home visits
        - 1955 September-1958 April (Box 35, Folder 1)
        - 1958 February-1959 June (Box 35, Folder 2)
        - 1959 August-1960 June (Box 35, Folder 3)
        - 1960 October-1961 June (Box 35, Folder 4)
        - 1961 September-1962 June (Box 35, Folder 5)
        - 1962 November-1964 July (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - Index headings, 1956-1962 (Box 36, Folder 1-5)
      - Kris Maury summary, 1951-1954 (Box 36, Folder 6)
      - Methodology
        - 1958 November-1959 July (Box 36, Folder 7)
        - 1959 September-1960 May (Box 36, Folder 8)
        - 1960 September-1961 September (Box 36, Folder 9)
        - 1961 September-1962 October (Box 36, Folder 10)
      - Outside observations
        - 1959 January-June (Box 37, Folder 1)
        - 1959 August-1960 April (Box 37, Folder 2)
        - 1960 September-1961 June (Box 37, Folder 3)
        - 1961-1964 (Box 37, Folder 4)
      - Pediatric contacts
        - 1959 January-May (Box 37, Folder 5)
        - 1959 October-1960 April (Box 37, Folder 6)
        - 1961 May (Box 37, Folder 7)
        - 1961 November (Box 37, Folder 8)
      - Psychological tests
        - 1954-1960 (Box 37, Folder 9)
        - 1961 (Box 37, Folder 10)
      - Research meetings
        - 1958 February-1959 June (Box 37, Folder 11)
        - Follow-up study, 1958 October (Box 38, Folder 1)
        - 1959 September-1960 June (Box 38, Folder 2)
        - 1960 September-1961 June (Box 38, Folder 3)
        - 1961 September-1962 July (Box 38, Folder 4)
        - 1962 October-1963 June (Box 38, Folder 5)
        - 1963 October-1964 May (Box 38, Folder 6)
      - Scrapbook, 1959-1969, undated (Box 38, Folder 7)
      - Summaries
        - 1958 September-December (Box 39, Folder 1)
        - 1958 December-1959 March (Box 39, Folder 2)
        - 1959 March-July (Box 39, Folder 3)
        - 1959 September-1960 January (Box 40, Folder 1)
        - 1960 January-March (Box 40, Folder 2)
        - 1960 March-June (Box 41, Folder 1)
        - 1960 September-December (Box 41, Folder 2)
        - 1961 January-April (Box 42, Folder 1)
        - 1961 April-July (Box 42, Folder 2)
        - 1961 September-December (Box 43, Folder 1)
        - 1962 January-April (Box 43, Folder 2)
        - 1962 April-July (Box 44, Folder 1)
        - 1962 September-December (Box 44, Folder 2)
        - 1962 December-1963 March (Box 44, Folder 3)
        - 1963 April-June (Box 44, Folder 4)
      - Follow-up and writings
        - 1950s-1960s (Box 45, Folder 1)
        - 1970s (Box 45, Folder 2)
        - 1981-1982 (Box 45, Folder 3)
        - 1983-1984 (Box 45, Folder 4)
        - 1985-1987 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Discontinued subjects
- Administrative files, 1950-2002, undated; Series II
  These records are restricted until January 1, 2050.
  - Instructions for taking research meeting notes, Undated (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - General research meetings, 1950-1953 (Box 53, Folder 2-4)
  - Prenatal (pregnancy study) issues, 1951 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Post-natal meetings, 1951 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Nursery meetings, 1950-1952 (Box 53, Folder 7-8)
  - Collaboration meetings, 1952-1953 (Box 53, Folder 9)
  - Research conferences, 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 10)
  - Summary of research meetings on pregnancy case histories, 1955-1958 (Box 53, Folder 11)
  - Pregnancy text, 1955-1956 (Box 53, Folder 12)
  - "Evaluative observations", 1957
  - Administrative, 1955-1963, 1985, undated (Box 55, Folder 1-4)
  - Sibling Study Group, 1977-1979 (Box 55, Folder 5-7)
  - Follow up, 1981-1982 (Box 55, Folder 8-9)
  - Information on coded names, 1956-1958 (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Western New England Psychoanalytic Institute, 2002 April 26
    - Master, 1 (Box 55A)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 55aU)
- Photographs, Undated; Series III
  - Discontinued subjects
- Katherine Wolf records, 1942-1963, undated; Series IV
  Longitudinal Study Data, boxes 59-84, is restricted until January 1, 2050 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - Longitudinal study data
    Longitudinal Study Data is restricted until January 1, 2050. Researchers wishing to use this the data before this date must secure written authorization from the Arnold Gesell Professor of Child Psychiatry, Pediatrics, and Psychology, Yale Child Study Center.
    - Discontinued subjects
      - Brown (1), 1950-1951 (Box 80, Folder 1-2)
      - DeAngelo (11), 1950-1951 (Box 80, Folder 20-21)
  - Correspondence
    - A, 1953-1957 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - American Psychological Association, 1949-1957 (Box 85, Folder 2)
    - Auersperg, Alfred, 1956-1960 (Box 85, Folder 3-4)
    - B, 1951-1965, undated (Box 85, Folder 5)
    - Bandler, Bernard, 1954-1955 (Box 85, Folder 6)
    - Bank Street College of Education, 1953-1954 (Box 85, Folder 7)
    - Bayley, Nancy, 1956 (Box 85, Folder 8)
    - Beck, James C., 1957-1958 (Box 85, Folder 9)
    - Benjamin, John, 1951-1959 (Box 85, Folder 10)
    - Bio-Sciences Information Exchange, 1954-1957 (Box 85, Folder 11)
    - Boston Study (See: Pavenstedt, Eleanor)
    - Brown, Janet L., 1956-1958 (Box 85, Folder 12)
    - Bury, Theodora, 1952-1958 (Box 85, Folder 13)
    - Buxton, Claude E., 1951-1953 (Box 85, Folder 14)
    - C, 1951-1958, undated (Box 85, Folder 15)
    - Campbell, Enid Hobart ( See: Pavenstedt, Eleanor)
    - Carter, Gordon, 1954 (Box 85, Folder 16)
    - Chance, Erika, 1953 (Box 85, Folder 17)
    - Child Development Center for Preschool Children (NY), 1956-1957 (Box 85, Folder 18)
    - Child Study Association of America, 1950-1960 (Box 85, Folder 19-22)
    - Child Study Center, 1953-1963 (Box 85, Folder 23-24)
    - Childcraft, 1952-1957 (Box 85, Folder 25)
    - City College of New York, 1950-1951 (Box 85, Folder 26)
    - Connecticut State Psychological Society, 1955-1957 (Box 85, Folder 30)
    - Cremerius, _________, 1958 (Box 85, Folder 31)
    - Crook, Dorothea, 1957-1958 (Box 86, Folder 1)
    - D, 1951-1955 (Box 86, Folder 2)
    - Davis, John L., 1956-1957 (Box 86, Folder 3)
    - E, 1951, 1962 (Box 86, Folder 4)
    - Escalona, Sibylle, 1951-1958 (Box 86, Folder 5)
    - F, 1950-1957 (Box 86, Folder 6)
    - G, 1951-1959 (Box 86, Folder 8)
    - Goodrich, D. Wells, 1957 (Box 86, Folder 9)
    - H, 1952-1957 (Box 86, Folder 10)
    - Harley, Marjorie, 1957, undated (Box 86, Folder 12)
    - I, 1953-1954, undated (Box 86, Folder 12)
    - Inhelder, Barbara, 1956-1960 (Box 86, Folder 13)
    - Iowa State University, 1957 (Box 86, Folder 14)
    - J, 1951-1959, undated (Box 86, Folder 15)
    - K, 1951-1957, undated (Box 86, Folder 17)
    - Knowlton, Barbara, 1951, undated (Box 86, Folder 20)
    - Kohn, Martin, 1953-1957 (Box 86, Folder 21)
    - L, 1951-1957 (Box 86, Folder 22)
    - Lesser, Gerald, 1953-1956 (Box 86, Folder 23)
    - Lorenz, Konrad, 1955-1957 (Box 86, Folder 24)
    - M, 1951-1959, undated (Box 86, Folder 25)
    - Marschak, Marianne, 1957-1962 (Box 86, Folder 26)
    - Miller, Neal, 1957-1958 (Box 86, Folder 27)
    - N, 1951, undated (Box 86, Folder 28)
    - Nagy, Maria, 1954-1956 (Box 86, Folder 29)
    - Nixon, Norman, 1953-1954 (Box 86, Folder 30)
    - O, 1952, 1957 (Box 86, Folder 31)
    - P, 1950-1957 (Box 86, Folder 32)
    - Pavenstedt, Eleanor, 1953-1957 (Box 86, Folder 33)
    - R, 1951-1957, undated (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - Rosenfeld, Eva, 1956 (Box 87, Folder 2)
    - S, 1952-1958 (Box 87, Folder 3)
    - Schmidt, Edith Taglicht, 1955 (Box 87, Folder 4)
    - Senn, Milton, 1953-1960 (Box 87, Folder 5)
    - Sigel, Irving, 1953-1954 (Box 87, Folder 6)
    - Spitz, René A., 1951-1958 (Box 87, Folder 7)
    - Spock, Benjamin, 1952-1954 (Box 87, Folder 8)
    - Stechler, Gerald ( See: Pavenstedt, Eleanor)
    - T, U, 1951-1956, undated (Box 87, Folder 9)
    - Tolmach, Regina, 1954-1957 (Box 87, Folder 10)
    - Towbin, Alan, 1954 (Box 87, Folder 11)
    - V, W, 1951-1957, undated (Box 87, Folder 12)
    - Washburn, Alfred, 1951-1956 (Box 87, Folder 13)
    - Y, Z, 1953-1957 (Box 87, Folder 14)
    - Yale University, Child Study Center (See: Child Study Center)
    - Yale University, Department of Psychology, 1953-1957 (Box 87, Folder 15)
  - Writings
    - "Origins of Individuality"
      - KW"s work folder, 1942-1957 (Box 88, Folder 1)
      - Early draft and notes [handwritten], 1954 (Box 88, Folder 2-3)
      - Typescript with handwritten annotations [corrected draft], circa 1956 (Box 88, Folder 4-10)
      - Revised typescript, circa 1956 (Box 88, Folder 11-17)
      - Introduction to case studies
        - Draft with corrections, 1956 September 27 (Box 88, Folder 18-19)
        - Notes of Katherine Wolf and A. Auersperg on manuscript, 1957 (Box 89, Folder 1)
        - Introduction and appendices, copy 1, 1958 (Box 89, Folder 2)
        - Last corrections, 1958 Spring (Box 89, Folder 3)
        - Sketches, Undated (Box 89, Folder 4-6)
        - Bibliography, Undated (Box 89, Folder 7)
      - Evaluations of manuscript, 1957-1958 (Box 89, Folder 8)
      - Notes on planning publication, 1957-1958 (Box 89, Folder 9)
    - "Guide for Conducting and Reporting Hospital Observations of the Child", 1957-1959 (Box 89, Folder 10-13)
    - "Manual of Instructions for the Pre-structured Observation Technique", circa 1950-1952 (Box 89, Folder 14-15)
- Families data (duplicates), 1950-1964; Series V
  - Discontinued subjects
- Additional material, 1951-1986; 1951-1955; Accession 2014-A-060
  Restricted until January 1, 2061
  - Lecture: "Some Aspects of a Family Interaction: A Psychoanalytic Study", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Draft publication, "A Dyanmic Biography Based on Direct Observation and Psychoanalytic Treatment in the First Ten Years with Follow-Up at Age 34", by S. Rituo, R. Lord, A. Naylor, S. Provence, and A. Solnit, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)